A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, projects, SG 1.1, Series 300 Latin America - Series 833 Lebanon FA386b
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Switzerland, 1922-1957; 803; 2 Cubic Feet; 5 __Boxes __2 cubic feet
  - Switzerland - Medical Sciences, 803.A
    - University of Zurich - Neuropsychiatry - (Reports, Items), 1940-1946 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - University of Zurich - Neuropsychiatry - (Reprints), 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - University of Zurich - Physiology - (Hess, W.R.) - (brain research), 1934, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - University of Zurich - Psychiatry - (Maier, Hans) - (brain research), 1933, 1935-1937 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - University of Zurich - Psychiatry - Surgical Clinic - (purchase of equipment), 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Switzerland - Natural Sciences and Agriculture, 803.D
    - Jungfraujoch Scientific Station - (Construction and Equipment), 1930-1935, 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Jungfraujoch Scientific Station - (no grant made), 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Technical High School, Zurich - Organic Chemistry - (Ruzicka, L.), 1936-1951, 1953-1957 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Technical High School, Zurich - Organic Chemistry - (Ruzicka, L.), 1936-1951, 1953-1957 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Technical High School, Zurich - Organic Chemistry - (Ruzicka, L.), 1936-1951, 1953-1957 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Technical High School, Zurich - Organic Chemistry - (Ruzicka, L.), 1936-1951, 1953-1957 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Technical High School, Zurich - Plant Physiology - (Frey-Wyssling, A.), 1939-1957 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Technical High School, Zurich - Plant Physiology - (Frey-Wyssling, A.), 1939-1957 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Technical High School, Zurich - Plant Physiology - (Frey-Wyssling, A.), 1939-1957 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Technical High School, Zurich - Plant Physiology - (Frey-Wyssling, A.) - (Reprints), 1940-1941; 8 Items (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - University of Berne - Botany - (Purchase of Equipment), 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - University of Berne - Botany - (Schopfer, W.H.), 1948-1954, 1956-1960 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - University of Berne - Organic Chemistry - (purchase of equipment), 1936-1942 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - University of Berne - Organic Chemistry - (purchase of equipment), 1936-1942 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - University of Berne - Physics - (Purchase of Films), 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - University of Berne - Physiology - (Purchase of Equipment), 1928, 1930-1932, 1935-1941 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - University of Berne - Physiology - (von Muralt, A.) - (travel grant, U.S.), 1942-1943, 1945-1948 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - University of Berne - Zoology - (Travel Grant, Denmark), 1938-1939 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - University of Geneva - Chemistry - (Purchase of Equipment), 1931, 1935-1937 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - University of Geneva - Chemistry - (Meyer, Kurt H.) - (cellulose and starch research), 1946, 1948-1954 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - University of Geneva - Chemistry - (Guyenot, Emile) - (purchase of equipment), 1929-1937 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - University of Zurich - Physiological Chemistry - (purchase of equipment), 1939-1941 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Switzerland - Humanities and Arts, 803.R
    - Bibliotheque Pour Tous - (Book Purchases) - (regional services development), 1937-1941 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Bibliotheque Pour Tous - (Book Purchases) - (regional services development), 1942-1943, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Bibliotheque Pour Tous - (Reports), 1932-1942; 32 Items contained in 52 & 53 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Bibliotheque Pour Tous - (Reports), 1932-1942; 32 Items contained in folders 52 & 53. (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Switzerland - Social Sciences, 803.S
    - Grabewsky, Adolf - (Political Science) - (Salary Support), 1936, 1938-1942 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Grabewsky, Adolf - (Political Science) - (Salary Support), 1936, 1938-1942 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Jacobsson, Per - Visit (U.S.) - (Economics), 1945-1946 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Silberschmidt, Max - (American History), 1934-1935 (Box 5, Folder 57)
- Near East Region, 1916, 1918-1919, 1924-1927; 804; 0.2 Cubic Feet; 1 __Box __0.2 cubic feet
  The Rockefeller Foundation's proposed Near East Commission never visited that region due to unsettled conditions after World War I. Two studies of medical education in that area were conducted, however, in 1916 and 1924-1927.
  Two subseries, as follows:
  804 (no program letter; general material which does not fit into a particular program area)
  804 A Medical sciences (research conducted in medical schools or medical research institutes, research directly applicable to the mental and physical health of human beings)
  - Near East Commission - (not sent), 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Near East Region - Medical Sciences, 804.A
    - NE - 1 Ward, Edwin St. John "Medical Education in the Near East", 1916 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - NE - 2 "Medical Education in Armenia, Palestine, and other minor Near East Countries (Preliminary Report)", 1924-1927 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Turkey, 1915-1950; 805; 0.4 Cubic Feet; 1 __Box __0.4 cubic feet
  Early Foundation interest in Turkey came in the areas of medical education and nursing. Grants were made in the 1920's and 1930's for various public health projects in Ankara and Istanbul. Support in the later 1940's came for a survey of nursing and a travel grant for a lecturer in economics.
  805 (no program letter; general material which does not fit into a particular program area)
  805 A Medical sciences (research conducted in medical schools or medical research institutes, research directly applicable to the mental and physical health of human beings)
  805 C Nursing (nursing education, public health nursing)
  805 I Malaria
  805 J Public health demonstrations, local health units
  805 L Public health education (schools of hygiene and public health
  805 S Social sciences
  Actual dates for this series are: 1915, 1917, 1921, 1923-1929, 1931-1941, 1946-1950.
  - COL - 1 Collins, Ralph K. "Public Health in Turkey,", 1926 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - COL - 1a Collins, Ralph K. "Public Health in Turkey: Appendix,", 1926 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Turkey - Medical Sciences, 805.A
    - Medical Education, 1915, 1917, 1921, 1923-1925 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - TUR - 1 "Medical Education in Turkey,", 1923-1927 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Turkey - Nursing, 805.C
    - (Nursing) - (Study of Conditions), 1923, 1926-1928, 1940, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - (Nursing) - (Study of Conditions), 1923, 1926-1928, 1940, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Varley, Margaret L. {"Nursing in Turkey: Preliminary Report with Recommendations,", 1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Turkey - Malaria, 805.I
    - (Malaria) - (no grant made), 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Turkey - Public Health Demonstrations, 805.J
    - (Public Health), 1927-1929 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Ankara Health Center, 1936-1941 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Istanbul - (Proposed Health Center), 1931-1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Turkey - Public Health Education, 805.L
    - Visits - (Refik Bey, Assim Bey), 1929 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Turkey - Social Sciences, 805.S
    - Istanbul University - Rustow, Alexander - (travel grant, economics), 1946-1948, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Crete, 1947-1949; 807; 0.2 Cubic Feet; 1 __Box __0.2 cubic feet
  One subseries covering the staffing of regional development work in Crete. Most of the individual folders consist of resumes of applicants who were not hired.
  - Regional Development - Personnel - (General), 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Regional Development - Personnel - Cavis, Alan - (Political science), 1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Regional Development - Personnel - Crosby, H. Lamar, Jr., 1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Regional Development - Personnel - Larsinos, George - (agriculture), 1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Regional Development - Personnel - Leggette, R. M. - (Water geologist), 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Regional Development - Personnel - Pavlakis, Achilles, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Regional Development - Personnel - Recruitment, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Regional Development - Personnel - Robertson, Doris - (nursing), 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Regional Development - Personnel - Shaffer, Newton W., 1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Regional Development - Staff - Macintosh, W.A., 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Cyprus, 1935-1940, 1944-1949; 809; 0.2 Cubic Feet; 1 __Box __0.2 cubic feet
  The Rockefeller Foundation sponsored anti-malaria work and hookworm control programs on Cyprus during the 1930's and 1940's.
  809 (no program letter; general material which does not fit into a particular program area)
  809 I Malaria
  - Soil Pollution, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - S - T Stratman - Thomas, Warren K. Diary, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cyprus - Malaria, 809.I
    - (Malaria), 1935-1940, 1944-1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - (Malaria), 1935-1940, 1944-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - BAL - 1 Balfour, Marshall C. "Cyprus - Malaria:Notes on Visit,", 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Israel, 1921-1929, 1931-1949; 825; 0.4 Cubic Feet; 1 __Box __0.4 cubic feet
  The Rockefeller Foundation's earliest activity in Israel (formerly Palestine) was in the fields of malaria and hookworm control. During the 1930's, the Foundation also sponsored refugee scholars who were placed on the faculty of Hebrew University. Later grants were made in the fields of jaundice research and sex research.
  825 (no program letter; general material which does not fit into a particular program area)
  825 A Medical sciences (research conducted in medical schools or medical research institutes, research directly applicable to the mental and physical health of human beings)
  825 D Natural sciences and agriculture (research usually conducted in departments outside of medical schools, research in pure science, veterinary medicine or agriculture)
  825 H Hookworm
  825 I Malaria
  825 R Humanities and arts
  825 S Social sciences
  - Hebrew University - Jaundice - (Kligler, I.V.), 1943-1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hebrew University - Jaundice - (Kligler, I.V.), 1943-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hebrew University - Sex Research, 1934-1937, 1939-1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Israel - Medical Sciences, 825.A
    - Hebrew University - Sex Research, 1934-1937, 1939-1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Hebrew University - Sex Research, 1934-1937, 1939-1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Hebrew University - Wertheimer, Ernst - (physiology, refugee), 1933-1934, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - HU - 1 Lambert, Robert A. "Report on Visit to Hebrew University Medical School", 1934 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Israel - Natural Sciences and Agriculture, 825.D
    - Hebrew University - Farkas, Ladislaus - (physical chemistry, refugee), 1933-1935, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Israel - Hookworm, 825.H
    - SCO - 1 Scott, J.A. "Preliminary Report of a Survey of Hookworm Disease, JaffaSub-District Palestine", 1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Israel - Malaria, 825.I
    - (Malaria), 1921-1929, 1931, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - CAR - 1 Carter, J.C. "Palestine - Malaria," 1929 CAR - 2 "Notes on Inspection of the Ruben and Jordan Areas," 1931 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - PUT - 2 Putnam, Persis "Malaria in Palestine: Statistical Review,", 1928 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Israel - Humanities and Arts, 825.R
    - Hebrew University - Polotsky, Jacob Hans - (Egyptologist, refugee), 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Israel - Social Sciences, 825.S
    - Hebrew University - Landshut, Siegfried - (sociology, refugee), 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Lebanon, 1920-1967; 833; 3.6 Cubic Feet; 12 __Boxes __3.6 cubic feet
  With the exception of a few general reports on medical education, The Rockefeller Foundation's interest was channeled entirely through the American University of Beirut. The Foundation gave support to the University's Medical School (1920-1967), to its Arabic Studies program (1948-1953) and School of Nursing (1927-1941). Although the files contain considerable material concerning the University's Department of Sociology, including a textbook and yearbooks, there is no record of any Foundation grant for its support during this period.
  833 (no program letter; general material which does not fit into a particular program area)
  833 A Medical sciences (research conducted in medical schools or medical research institutes, research directly applicable to the mental and physical health of human beings)
  833 C Nursing (nursing education, public health nursing)
  833 R Humanities and arts
  833 S Social sciences
  - American University of Beirut - Engineering - (Bulletin), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American University of Beirut - Engineering - Ten Year Development Plan, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American University of Beirut - Engineering - Yearbook, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Health, 1930-1931, 1943-1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Health, 1930-1931, 1943-1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - MIL - 1 Milam, D.F. "Report on Syria,", 1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - MIL - 2 Milam, D.F. "Report on Lebanon,", 1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - MIL - 2a Milam, D.F. "Survey of Public Health Services in Lebanon,", 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Lebanon - Medical Sciences, 833.A
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School), 1926-1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School), 1926-1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School), 1926-1941 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School), 1926-1941 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School), 1926-1941 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School), 1926-1941 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School), 1926-1941 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School), 1926-1941 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School), 1942-1959 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School), 1942-1959 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School), 1942-1959 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School), 1942-1959 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School), 1942-1959 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School), 1942-1959 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School), 1960-1967 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School), 1960-1967 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School), 1960-1967 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School), 1960-1967 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School) - (Heiser, Victor, Report), 1921 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School) - (Reports), 1922, 1925-1928; 7 items (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School) - Reports, 1930-1933, 1935-1938; 12 Items contained in 29 & 30 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School) - Reports, 1930-1933, 1935-1938; 12 Items contained in 29 & 30 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School) - Report (Annual), 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School) - Reports - (Planning and Development), 1931, 1960; 2 items (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School) - (Report) "Request for Support of Medical Division Development,", 1952 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School) - Bacteriology - (Dennis, E.W., Purchase of Equipment), 1935-1936 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School) - Biological Chemistry, 1934-1937, 1945-1949, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School) - Biological Chemistry, 1934-1937, 1945-1949, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School) - Pharmacology, 1934-1938 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School) - President's Annual Report, 1953-1954 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School) - Publications, 1932, 1952; 2 items (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School) - Ten Year Plan Preliminary Report - *see box 12, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School) - Treasurer of the Faculty Report, 1930-1931, 1933-1934 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School) - Visits - (Shultz, Philip L.) - (Slavin, Howard) - (Whipple, Allen O.), 1946-1947 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Heiser, Victor G "Extracts from notes re Beirut, Syria and abstracts from personal Diary", 1922 (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - Lebanon Hospital - (no grant made), 1924-1926 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - SY - 1 Pearce, Richard M. and Carter, W.S. "Medical Education in Syria", 1924-1927 (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - American University of Beirut - (Medical School) - Ten Year Plan Preliminary Report, 1962 (Box 12, Folder data_value_missing_ef4de4c78f866e2492fee9dbcdf24b72)
  - Lebanon - Nursing, 833.C
    - American University of Beirut - Health Center, 1927-1934 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - American University of Beirut - Nursing, 1927, 1930-1939, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - American University of Beirut - Nursing, 1927, 1930-1939, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - Lebanon - Humanities and Arts, 833.R
    - American University of Beirut - Arabic Studies - (no grant given), 1939-1941 (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - American University of Beirut - Arabic Studies, 1948-1953 (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - American University of Beirut - Arabic Studies, 1948-1953 (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - American University of Beirut - Arabic Studies, 1948-1953 (Box 7, Folder 52)
    - American University of Beirut - Arabic Studies, 1948-1953 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - American University of Beirut - Arabic Studies, 1954-1964 (Box 8, Folder 54)
    - American University of Beirut - Arabic Studies, 1954-1964 (Box 8, Folder 55)
    - American University of Beirut - Arabic Studies, 1954-1964 (Box 8, Folder 56)
    - American University of Beirut - Arabic Studies, 1954-1964 (Box 8, Folder 57)
    - American University of Beirut - Arabic Studies, 1954-1964 (Box 8, Folder 58)
    - American University of Beirut - (Humanities, general support), 1931-1933 (Box 8, Folder 59)
    - American University of Beirut - (Humanities, general support), 1934-1941 (Box 9, Folder 60)
  - Lebanon - Social Sciences, 833.S
    - American University of Beirut - (Social Sciences) "Report submitted by the Faculty of the American University of Beirut concerning the opportunity to train students for service in the Near East through Commerce and the Social Sciences", 1926 (Box 9, Folder 61)
    - American University of Beirut - (Social Sciences) "Statement to Serve as a Basis for an Appeal to The Rockefeller Foundation", 1929 (Box 9, Folder 62)
    - American University of Beirut - (Social Sciences) - Reports, 1930-1933; 11 items contained in 63 thru 66 (Box 9, Folder 63)
    - American University of Beirut - (Social Sciences) - Reports, 1930-1933; 11 items contained in 63 thru 66 (Box 9, Folder 64)
    - American University of Beirut - (Social Sciences) - Reports, 1930-1933; 11 items contained in 63 thru 66 (Box 9, Folder 65)
    - American University of Beirut - (Social Sciences) - Reports, 1930-1933; 11 items contained in 63 thru 66 (Box 9, Folder 66)
    - American University of Beirut - (Social Sciences) - Reports, 1934-1935; 2 items (Box 10, Folder 67)
    - American University of Beirut - (Social Sciences) - Report (Treasurer), 1933-1934 (Box 10, Folder 68)
    - American University of Beirut - (Social Sciences) - Report (Miscellaneous), 1932, 1938, 1940; 3 items (Box 10, Folder 69)
    - American University of Beirut - (Sociology Department) - Dodd, S.C. "Social Relationships in the Near East,", 1931 (Box 10, Folder 70)
    - American University of Beirut - (Sociology Department) - Yearbook, 1928 (Box 10, Folder 71)
    - American University of Beirut - (Sociology Department) - Yearbook, 1929-1931 (Box 11, Folder 72)
    - American University of Beirut - (Sociology Department) - Yearbook, 1929-1931 (Box 11, Folder 73)